Guide to the Marcia Nardi Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marcia Nardi collection
1949-1983
YCAL MSS 70
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(2 boxes)
The Marcia Nardi collection contains correspondence and writings documenting her work as a poet between 1949 and 1983. The collection contains letters to Nardi by Louise Bogan, Marguerite Caetani, Randall Jarrell, Norman Holmes Pearson, Alec Waugh, Thornton Wilder, and others, most offering personal and professional advice and assistance in her efforts to complete a volume of poems. There is also a manuscript miscellany, "The New Helicon," in the hand of John Edmunds and a typescript of Nardi's poem "Femelle de l'homme." The collection also contains John Edmunds Papers pertaining to Nardi including correspondence from Nardi to Edmunds and typescript drafts of her unpublished book "Collected Poems."
Nardi, Marcia, 1901-1990
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Marcia Nardi on the Danford Barney and F. O. Matthiesson Fund, 1968, and from the Turtle Island Book Shop on the Elizabeth Wakeman Dwight Memorial Fund, 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Marcia Nardi (1901-1990)
Marcia Nardi, American poet, was born Lilian Massell in Boston and attended Girls' Latin School and Wellesley College, which she left in 1921 to live in Greenwich Village and to write. During this period Nardi contributed poetry and book reviews to publications such as the Nation, New Republic, Quarterly Review of Literature, the New York Times, and the New York Herald Tribune. In 1926 her son Paul was born, and Nardi was forced to take a variety of jobs to support him and herself. In 1942 she began a correspondence with William Carlos Williams, who used long sections of her letters in Books I and II of Paterson. Her Poems was published by Alan Swallow in 1956, and she received a Guggenheim fellowship in the following year. Nardi worked extensively with John Edmunds between 1972 and 1983 with the intention of publishing a collection of her poetry; however this project did not result in a publication before Nardi's death in 1990.
Scope and Contents
The Marcia Nardi collection contains correspondence and writings documenting her work as a poet between 1949 and 1983. The collection contains letters to Nardi by Louise Bogan, Marguerite Caetani, Randall Jarrell, Norman Holmes Pearson, Alec Waugh, Thornton Wilder, and others, most offering personal and professional advice and assistance in her efforts to complete a volume of poems. There is also a manuscript miscellany, "The New Helicon," in the hand of John Edmunds and a typescript of Nardi's poem "Femelle de l'homme." The collection also contains John Edmunds Papers pertaining to Nardi including correspondence from Nardi to Edmunds and typescript drafts of her unpublished book "Collected Poems."
Arrangement
The Marcia Nardi Collection is organized into two series: Marcia Nardi Papers and John Edmunds Papers. Each series is organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Writings. The Marcia Nardi Papers were processed in 1993 and have not been re-processed. The John Edmunds Papers were processed in 2007.
Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Correspondence; Women poets, American -- 20th Century; Bogan, Louise, 1897-1970; Caetani, Marguerite, 1880-1963; Edmunds, John, 1913-1986; Jarrell, Randall, 1914-1965; Nardi, Marcia, 1901-1990; Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1909-1975; Ransom, John Crowe, 1888-1974; Shapiro, Karl, 1913-2000; Waugh, Alec, 1898-1981; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975; Edward MacDowell Association
- Marcia Nardi Papers, 1949-1965; Series I; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Writings.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains Marcia Nardi's Papers including incoming correspondence and some writings (a few poems, reviews, and a manuscript anthology containing other writers' poetry entitled "The New Helicon"). Also included is a letter from Louise Bogan to Robert Phelps.
  - Correspondence, 1949-1965
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
    - The Atlantic Monthly, 1954, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bogan, Louise, 1955-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Botteghe, Oscure, 1956, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Caetani, Marguerite, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Edward MacDowell Association, Inc., 1954 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Jarrell, Mary, 1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Ransom, John Crowe, 1952 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Shapiro, Karl, 1952 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Waugh, Alec, 1954-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Wilder, Thornton, 1953-1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 12-18)
    - Bogan, Louise to Robert Phelps, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Writings, 1954, undated
    - Birthday Poem (to Alec Waugh), typescript, signed, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Reviews, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "The New Helicon", bound manuscript, 1954 December (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Contains Nardi's poem "Was it the Honey-Hearted Vowel?" (transcribed by Thornton Wilder)
- John Edmunds Papers, circa 1950, 1972-1983; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  The series contains Nardi's correspondence with John Edmunds (including photocopy of letter to Nardi from William Carlos Williams) and drafts documenting her work with Edmunds to publish her collected poems. Also includes annotated copy of Nardi's book entitled Poems.
  - Correspondence, 1950, 1972-1983
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Nardi, Marcia to John Edmunds, 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Nardi, Marcia to John Edmunds, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 24-29)
    - Nardi, Marcia to John Edmunds, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
    - Williams, William Carlos to Marcia Nardi, photocopy of original, circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Writings, 1956, 1982
    - Poems, printed version, corrected, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      Denver, CO.: Alan Swallow, 1956. With Nardi's corrections.
    - Poetry, typescript, with holograph corrections, circa 1982 (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
    - "Collected Poems", typescript, preliminary draft with holograph corrections, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - "Collected Poems", typescript, final draft, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 37)